latch latch
latex L
latexy how do you say it I don't
know should we go should we ask chat GPT
what chat GPT says chat GPT can't
produce anything I wonder I wonder if I
can make chat GPT like actually
pronounce it should we try it I'm GNA
try it right now yeah I'm gonna try it
I'm I'm G to try it right now uh how do
you pronounce
lch everybody fights over this the
pronunciation for latex is
[Laughter]
latex well that was wrong I know that's
wrong
uh 10 seconds in is it is it really I
who who's that person so okay so latch
is pronounced latch
leat or
latch kth pronounces it latek
K himself produces it as lch oh well
there you go k is the guy who made it Mr
Donald k um why do you care about this
technology you're definitely going to
hear about it over time so this video is
not to get you going on this it's just
to help you not sound like you don't
know what you're talking take you to
level one knowledge in on on our
10-point scale um that means you know
what it is you don't maybe not used it
maybe don't need to use it but you need
to know what it is
um so lwtech is this Tech actually let's
ask chat GPT again I I like this this is
fun uh what is lwtech I'm going to read
it from see how well I want to see how
well chat GPT does uh L is a high
quality type setting system you guys
know what type setting is remember type
setting think of think of like an old
medieval guy with like lead you know on
on like a a thing and they're setting
you know lead type you know they're
setting fonts like individual character
fonts and they they're putting leting in
between uh each of the letters so they
have spacing you know it's like it's
something that you know people like me
like really like actually I really love
typ setting I think I I would love to
get myself like an actual old school
press and and do type setting I think
it's really that's what type setting is
so type Setters used to be paid to like
make these single pages and they would
like it's really really cool stuff right
it's almost like blacksmithing but for
like books book bindings and bookmaking
stuff like that so that's what type
setting is um so let's take is a high
quality type selling system in other
words this digital type setting system
uh that includes features designed for
the production of Technical and
scientific documentation that's what
makes it special it's a programming
language used primarily for writing
documents in fields such as mathematics
physics computer science and economics
engineering and is allowed complex
mathematical equations algorithms
symbols latch is also used for types
setting articles books and other
Publications in fact latch is the
standard in the academic world for
producing textbooks pretty much um and
there's been a you know there's been a
lot of different approaches that come to
latch um this video is is linked to the
video about markdown because you know
one of the things when I uh when I
thought about how to potentially
reinvent uh the worldwide web uh which I
absolutely tried uh something called the
knowledge exchange grid you know the
question kept coming up if you wanted to
have a
unified uh method or Syntax for all
knowledge um what are what types of
knowledge would you have to be able to
convey um obviously text is the big one
right but then if you think um yeah Tech
was originally the art the type set of
the art of computer programming yeah
thank you for that Ronnie yeah so you
know the other piece of this is
inevitably you're going to ask yourself
how do I make a diagram that's
reproducible that I can represent as
text right how do I make a anything how
do I make a very complicated uh
mathematical equation um and you know
how we we did another video on scalable
vector graphics versus uh rasterized
images which is you know little dots
versus
instructions and latch is in the
instructions category in fact I I'm
going to go ahead and ask Chad GPT uh
what is the relationship between uh
ltech and PDF or or postcript postcript
was the instructions set language
created to tell mostly Laser Printers
how to draw our documents in a way that
was you know consistent and types set
down to the you know the individual DPI
uh latch is a type setting system blah
PDF and postcript are both file formats
that can be used to save and documents
they are designed to present documents
so that's the relationship when you
prepare a document using latch you can
convert or compile that document into a
PDF or postcript file this is typically
done so that the document can be easily
shared or published the PDF or postcript
file will maintain the same formatting
appearance in other words the use of
latch to create and format your document
and then you can use PDF or postcript to
share the document all right so that
would seem to me that there is no
relationship um that lwtech is its own
instruction set about how things should
be viewed and seen and uh postcript and
PDF which is built on top of postcript
um um by the Adobe company of course and
originally Apple are instructions
specifically for how to draw that thing
on the printer or on the screen um and
yes I am and so PDF is in a uh PDF is an
evaluated PS file to prevent arbitrary
code execution within the within the
project okay right so so this becomes
that's the extent of it now why do you
care and what does this have to do with
markdown well if you're trying to do
mathematical symbols and by that I mean
um so let's see if we can show you here
uh math
examples uh examples using L Tech okay
so
um I'm trying to see here's an example
for you um here's a random hit uh from a
math department math departments live
for latch um as you can see here um oops
here we go so here we can see that the
dollar sign inline we didn't do we
talked about inline formatting before uh
we see that the dollar sign inline
formatting is there's a language for
representing um this type set equation
ax to the 2 plus b to the x uh plus b *
x uh plus cal0 and you can see how they
get represented um you can see that
there are limits look at here's a here's
some lotac code down here for limits
and you I mean it goes without saying
that you cannot have uh you know a
method of knowledge exchange and
knowledge sharing without latch it does
make me wonder quite frankly why latch
was not included in the original design
coming from CERN of all places um you
know and here we go here's an actual
block uh this is a lwtech block notice
it has two dollar signs okay okay so the
double dollar sign so the reason that
this is related to markdown is because
latch has been added to every major
version of markdown that is supported on
the in in interwebs right now uh which I
actually think is
tremendously uh huge news uh that
includes GitHub flavor markdown um and
while it's true that it's not all of
latch we'll get there
it's generally true to say that lwtech
is now the industry standard for sharing
mathematical equations period And if you
are doing anything in math and that
includes machine learning um you must
learn it at some point and I have a fun
story about this so I I I I don't know
latte very well I have to go look it up
if I ever want to do any of this I don't
do a lot of mathematical writing even
though I have like 300 level calculus in
college
um and I I was sharing latch and and and
um specifically kex and math Jacks uh
which are all related uh we'll get into
that later but I shared it with somebody
that I was mentoring and um quite a
quite a brilliant kid at the time and um
he must have been 13 and I mean this
this is the kind of guy who got sent
this is no no kidding he this is a
separate story but he he got sent to the
principal's office for using the Linux
terminal um through SSH into skill stch
so he could do some of his project
because he was bored during his other
class and somebody saw him with a
terminal open on his Mac and they
reported him for hacking his teacher
didn't know what he was doing sent him
to principles and he had to sit there
and justify to the principal that he was
not hacking
anything that's a true story that
actually happened um so this same guy um
was taking notes in his math class in
his math and chemist class in latch and
one time I was like I looked over his
shoulder because I I taught him markdown
and some of that stuff and exposed him
to it and I exposed him to pandoc which
is which is what all the you know
invented by a Berkeley Professor for for
writing all this crazy amazing stuff and
and so so then you know I I was like
what you know he like oh here he was
just like randomly working on his stuff
he wasn't even really showing it to me
and I looked up go what the hell is that
he's like oh that's my notes like what
and he he had been taking his notes in
markdown and latch for school and he
basically wrote his own textbook I mean
it was the quality of the typ setting of
his markdown page um you know you it's
particularly impressive when it's like
these these these these big sections
like this you know because it's these
like big monstrous equations and he he
he was so bored in his class that he
decided to learn latch this this in like
Junior ey and he is in L and so he he
learned it and then he started writing
all his equations and it made it more
fun for him plus you know you get the
thing wrong and and so he had he had
basically types set his all of his notes
using latch and and markdown and I was
just so impressed I was like his
teachers must have hated
him because he was literally producing
textbooks they have no idea what
markdown even is um and you know I just
I just love that story because I mean it
was just so intense so like matrices and
things like this you know um so I mean
if there's at least one person out there
who has a little bit more fun taking
notes know who hears about ltech you
know and math Jacks and ktech and and
then you know maybe maybe something good
will come with in this video I'm not
going to teach you how to do it because
I don't know how to do it never done it
I I always have to look it up every time
I want to do it um and quite frankly you
don't need it right the only time you
need it is if you need math and that
brings us to the next topic what is math
Jack and what are lwtech uh and what
does it have to do so what is uh ktech
let's talk about that one
first uh kch I guess is a script for
type sitting math and web browser
developed by KH Academy it is designed
to WR mathematical notation fast and
easy learning format unlike other
scripts CCH doesn't require a web
browser machine to do anything it
renders equations server side so CCH uh
is a form of
latch uh H yeah yeah you can do pretty
much anything with ltech um it was
invented by Donald kth I'm pretty sure
um to to do his first uh book and he
wrote his own language to make the book
um and you can use lch for presentations
you can do it for all kinds of different
things uh there is one other thing and
and that is math Jacks now math Jax is a
open source JavaScript display engine
that produces high quality mathematical
type setting uh in a web browser it uses
um webbased sponse SVG and HTML uh to
display mathematical symbols in equation
mathjax is comparable to screen readers
for accessibility blah so mathjax
actually supports cek or whatever and
but the difference is is that math Jax
is in the client right so um when we use
we're going to learn uh I'll probably do
an extra video on how to use make dos
which is what I use um for skill stack
let me show you uh so make do is the is
the tool that I use um to take this
markdown and it uses python markdown and
converts it into um you know what what
what you see here so so here's here's
the
documentation um what does this have to
do with with uh ltech well I've actually
added in the material theme um the
support for I think math Jax maybe I
didn't oh I didn't add it to this one no
I didn't okay I don't have it in mind I
take it all back
um but you can you can add you can add
the point is you can add support for
math jaxs which is a JavaScript library
which will render the equations in the
web browser right and any of that stuff
can then be saved as a PDF and printed
um the difference is that's I think K
CCH or whatever is server side and latch
of course requires all a whole bunch of
other stuff um if you know Linux and
we'll talk about this later uh if you
know about Man pages so man LS
um this is using postcript but there um
there are forms of men pages that can be
created using latch as well so latch is
generally considered to have a pretty
steep learning curve um it's not for
everybody and U math Jacks which is
mostly just the math part of latch
allows latch to be included in markdown
and so the last thing we have to cover
is how to put it into your markdown um
and that the only thing you need to know
there is quite simply um if your
platform supports it you want to use $2
signs um in your own code block right uh
actually let's let's see let's see let's
let's try this shall we try this let's
try this let's try it's always more fun
to experiment so where is my
stuff I'm trying to find it oh it's over
here over here right all right let's go
make a let's make a test I just kind of
want to see it let's try it yeah yeah
yeah yeah let's add a new file create a
new
file let's call it MD
lmd
um this is uh some law tag I think it's
actually rendering it using using matchx
we'll paste it in there now something I
do know is pretty sure you have to put
this on a separate line I don't know
I don't know let's let's try it let's
see what happens I know this works Pand
dog so I don't I've never used it with
GitHub GitHub apparently has support for
those so let's go ahead and try um
commit
changes uh LTE
and is displayed to the user okay yep
there we go check it out wow look at
that you see
that and tell uh it's displayed to the
user that's very cool so there you go
um and and let's go ahead and say
um uh and what about stuff in line like
and this can be something simple uh is
it is pi a thing I can't
remember I don't cancel
preview oh yeah p is a thing um let's
actually find something better though to
display let's find some inline stuff
that's more
fun um again I don't know what I'm doing
so
uh let's find a good oh here's a pretty
one I like this oh look at this uh it's
square root look at that for example in
square root blah blah blah oh wow look
at that isn't that pretty so
copy and um just as a reminder what if
you want to show the actual text the way
they're doing it um let's try this let's
preview that oh look at that look at
that pretty pretty pretty thing
and so but if if you wanted to
say uh which is I did a back tick here
remember the back tick thing that says
verbatim
uh
uh uh in
ltech okay so that should there we go so
so if you want to see the actual source
code you see it there and you see it
there and I mean this pretty much it
that's pretty dang cool don't you admit
that is so cool so that's how you do it
that's what latch is that's what Max is
that's what kch is you're going to hear
about that stuff if you have a need for
it you can pretty much use it everywhere
the fact that you can use it on GitHub
now is tremendously encouraging and
exciting um you can use it in pandoc of
course you have been in for a very very
long time um and you can use it in make
dos too and in the world of AI where
math is is more and more a thing um you
know reach for it and use it if you know
how and you need to if I were if I were
going to be doing notes again I would
definitely learn it I don't know it So
eventually I probably do want to learn
it myself um so that's it have fun with
that